Edward E Griebel Jr.

edgriebel@gmail.com • 585-705-1093 • www.edgriebel.com github.com/edgriebel • linkedin.com/in/edgriebel

SUMMARY

Language-Agnostic Full Stack Developer with over 20 years of success creating software solutions. Wide breadth of experience in multiple industries, languages, tools, and third-party applications demonstrates success. Excitement about creating code to deliver high quality systems that support business growth.

Selected expertise: Java, Python, J2EE/JavaEE, MySQL, SQL, PL/SQL, JavaScript, JMS, RabbitMQ, Cognos, AppDynamics.

PROFESSIONAL WORK EXPERIENCE

Marqeta Inc.

May 2020 - Present

Lead Software Engineer

- Work closely with peer developers, product owners, and operations teams to create a new credit product including processing, accounting, statementing, and user-level APIs.
- Collaborate on creating processes and procedures to support development and maintenance activities.
- Mentor, guide, and be an example for other developers on the team for designs and general software engineering practices

Technologies: Java, MySQL, Spring Boot, Docker, jOOQ

Rochester Institute of Technology

August 2017 – Present

Adjunct Professor

- Currently teaching 3-credit undergraduate course in professional software engineering practices.
- Previous courses taught include undergraduate courses in Java and DBMS/SQL.

Logical Operations

Occasionally since January 2020

Consultant

Provide industry best practices and expertise for new courses in Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, and Data Science.

Catalant Technologies

June 2019 – March 2020

Principal Software Engineer

- Determine performance issues impacting system scalability and work with technical owners for prioritization and resolution
- Create and build consensus on engineering best practices to improve developer productivity and long-term supportability
- Create new features for customers and tools to enhance developer productivity
- Mentor and guide junior developers in Catalant's development environment and software engineering practices

Technologies: Python, Flask, JavaScript, MySQL, Bootstrap, Docker, Elasticsearch

Paychex June 2013 – June 2019

Middleware Architect

- Created system to rebalance 20,000 databases among 200 pools in Azure cloud using algorithmic, statistical, and machine learning techniques with TensorFlow, Pandas, NumPy, Jupyter, and scikit-learn in a Python pipeline.
- Built internal inventory system with web and REST APIs providing a single source of truth for virtualized and physical hosts, JVMs, CLRs, databases, and middleware. Relationships sourced from external management systems including AppDynamics, Puppet/Facter, ServiceNow, and Oracle.
- Created custom Chaos Monkey implementation to randomly kill middleware appliances and Java processes daily in production and non-production environments. The Chaos Monkey was monitored and controlled by a Spring Boot web application and Splunk dashboard.
- Implemented AppDynamics on over 20,000 JVMs to replace our custom built system that collected and monitored JVM metrics and send alerts via SNMP and SMTP.

Technologies: Java, JavaScript, JQuery-UI, Oracle PL/SQL, Scikit-Learn, Python, AppDynamics, Application Performance Monitoring (APM), ClearCase, Ant, Git, JUnit, Vagrant

2010 - 2013

Senior Software Engineer

- Fullstack Java/Oracle/ActiveMQ JMS developer for IoT system. Lead the integration and upgrade of Cognos Business Intelligence with IoT system using Groovy and Java.
- Internal technical consulting with professional services and product management teams.

Technologies: Java, JavaScript, Oracle PL/SQL, Hudson/Jenkins, Cognos, Business Intelligence

Paychex

 Lead for team of five to create Java/JavaScript front end and webapp for an existing internal fat client, and upgrade two existing web applications to contemporary standards. Used Hudson to create a CI/CD pipeline to QA environment. Mentored new developers, delivered technical training and technical consulting.

Frontier Communications

 Created Java applications to build DSL circuits and track sales commissions. Automated generation of Excel spreadsheets from Hyperion EssBase saving \$200,000 annually (two FTEs).

Global Crossing (division of Level3)

Lead multi-site teams to create Java and Perl CGI telecom applications.

JP Morgan Chase

Created trading systems in C/C++ and tactical applications for equity derivatives and HFT trading desks.

BlackRock Financial Management

■ Developed systems in C/C++ for MBS mortgage, Treasury, and Repo trading desks.

EDUCATION

Georgia Institute of Technology

M.S. in Computer Science

Expected December 2022

Concentrations in Computing Systems and Machine Learning

Bucknell University

B.S. in Computer Engineering

- Senior design project creating reference implementation of DHCP protocol for RFCs 1531 and 1534
- Concentrations in Digital Electronics and Geology

CERTIFICATIONS AppDynamics Certified Implementations Professional

November 2016

AWARDS

Paychex Paragon Award for Resiliency, Paychex

January 2019

Every year, five projects are chosen across Paychex that demonstrate resiliency, exceptional delivery, operational efficiency, etc. Our project, "Adaptive Load Balancing", was chosen. It routes requests in F5 BigIP GTM and LTMs across servers and data centers based on server load, real-time statistics, and other measures. Adaptive Load Balancing has reduced outages and improved response times for services using it.

AppDynamics Scale Award, AppDynamics

November 2015

Awarded by AppDynamics to the company that was able to quickly deploy the AppDynamics tool across the most complex environment. Our team deployed the AppDynamics tool to over 2,000 JBoss, WebLogic, and Windows IIS servers across production and non-production environments.

ACTIVITIES

Leader, Boy Scouts and Cub Scouts **FAA Certified Private Pilot**

2007 - Present

[Resume written in LAFX, compiled on 2021-05-05]